A Guide to the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) FA079
Rockefeller Archive Center
American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) records
undated
FA079
Rockefeller Archive Center
33.0 cubic ft. 80 document cases
American International Association for Economic and Social Development.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research without restriction.
Related Archival Materials note
See also AIA material in the Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, RG 4, Series AIA-IBEC.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains correspondence, memoranda, quarterly reports, and publications of the AIA and its various programs, as well as administrative materials.
Arrangement note
The AIA collection is arranged into three categories: General (folders 1-131), arranged alphabetically; Quarterly Reports (folders 132-310), arranged chronologically; and Publications (folders 311-534), arranged using Appendix III of "The AIA Story" by Martha Dalrymple. In each division, material has further been grouped alphabetically by program title. The AIA photographs have been arranged into a separate series.
Biographical/Historical note
The American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) (1946-1968), was established by Nelson A. Rockefeller in July 1946 as a privately financed non-profit philanthropic organization which aimed to promote "self-development and better standards of living, together with understanding and cooperation" in Latin America. The AIA worked closely with local governments and other established organizations to develop programs which could eventually be supported and managed locally. Primarily, the AIA's activities focused on rural rehabilitation and agricultural development, with concentrated efforts on cooperative programs with the governments of Brazil and Venezuela. The AIA was also active in agricultural research and nutritional education as well as improving local roads, communications, and primary education.
AIA programs included the Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR), Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA), Council of Rural Development (CBR), and Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP).
File Plan note
IV 3B 02
Agriculture; Brazil; Home economics; International relations; Latin America; United States; Venezuela
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Aims and Objectives/Guiding Principles, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Reports, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Reports, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Reports, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Reports, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Report 1960 - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Report 1962 - Mock-up (Box 1, Folder 7)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Report 1962 - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 8)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Annual Report 1962 - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Appraisal of Major Programs, by French and Jones, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Articles, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Articles, by Griffing, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - By-Laws and Incorporation Certificate (Box 2, Folder 13)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Correspondence/Memorandum (Misc.), 1948-1959, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Crawford, W. L., 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Film Script - "Design for Hemisphere Action", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - "Highlights", 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - History (Box 2, Folder 18)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - History - Dalrymple - Notes - AIA, PIDR, IRI Research (Box 2, Folder 19)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - History - Dalrymple - Notes - Council of Rural Development (CBR) (Box 2, Folder 20)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - History - Dalrymple - Notes - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) (Box 3, Folder 21)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - History - Dalrymple - Notes - Inter-American Rural Youth Program (PIJR) (Box 3, Folder 22)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Home Economics, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Industrial Education - Quarterly Report, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Industrial Education - Report on Experimental Institute, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Industrial Education - Teacher Training, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - "Influence of American Private Enterprise in the Venezuelan Economy" (Box 3, Folder 27)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Monthly Reports, September 1959-May 1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Agricultural Scholarships, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, 1960-September 1961 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, October-December 1961 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, January-September 1962 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, October 1962-February 1963 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, March-October 1963 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, November-December 1963 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Chile, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Council of Rural Development (CBR) - General, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Council of Rural Development (CBR) - General, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Publications (Box 4, Folder 39)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Special Studies, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - IRI Division, 1960-February 1961 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - IRI Division, May 1961-March 1962 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - IRI Division, April 1962-June 1963 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - IRI Division, July-October 1963 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Costa Rica, 1957-November 1960 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Costa Rica, December 1960-April 1962 (Box 5, Folder 46)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Costa Rica, May-April 1963 (Box 5, Folder 47)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Costa Rica, January-June 1963 (Box 5, Folder 48)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Costa Rica, July 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Costa Rica, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 50)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Ecuador, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 51)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Uruguay, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Uruguay, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Uruguay (Personnel Newsletter), 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 54)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Uruguay (Personnel Newsletter), 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - General, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 56)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 57)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, January 1961 (Box 7, Folder 58)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, February 1961 (Box 7, Folder 59)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, March 1961-April 1961 (Box 7, Folder 60)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, May 1961-March 1962 (Box 7, Folder 61)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, April-August 1962 (Box 7, Folder 62)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil, September 1962-1966 (Box 7, Folder 63)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil - Planalto Survey, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 64)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Brazil - Planalto Survey, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 65)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Colombia, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 66)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Paraguay, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 67)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Venezuela, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 68)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Council - Philip Glick, 1960-April 1962 (Box 8, Folder 69)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Council - Philip Glick, May-June 1962 (Box 8, Folder 70)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Council - Philip Glick, July-September 1962 (Box 8, Folder 71)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - New York Office - Projects - Inter-American Rural Development Council - Philip Glick, November 1962-January 1964 (Box 9, Folder 72)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Newsletter #1-19, October-December 1951 (Box 9, Folder 73)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Newsletter #20-40, January-August 1952 (Box 9, Folder 74)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Operating Reports, 1950-1952 (Box 9, Folder 75)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Personnel Procedures and Policy Manual, 1952, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 76)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - "Proposed Program in Venezuela" by John Camp, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 77)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports (Condensed), 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 78)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports (Condensed), 1962 (Box 9, Folder 79)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports (Condensed), 1963 (Box 9, Folder 80)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports (Condensed), 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 81)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports (Condensed), 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 82)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Questionnaires - House Foreign Affairs Committee & Treasury Department, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 83)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Report to Oil Company Sponsors, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 84)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Review, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 85)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Review, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 86)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Vocational Training Project Publications (Box 10, Folder 87)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Annuals - Distribution (Box 10, Folder 88)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Financial Report, 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 89)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Handbook (Box 10, Folder 90)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Program Study - Farm Families, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 91)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Programa, 1954-1956 (Box 11, Folder 92)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Quarterly Report, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 93)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Training Course, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 94)
- Association of Credit and Rural Assistance (ACAR) - Annual Report, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 95)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 96)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Family Progress Reports- Instructions, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 97)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Financial Report, 1948-1951 (Box 11, Folder 98)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Home Economics Planning Guide (Box 11, Folder 99)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Instruction Guides for Rural Teachers (Box 11, Folder 100)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Manual de Procedimientos Tecnicos y Administrativos, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 101)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Newsletter #1-17, September 1956-February 1957 (Box 11, Folder 102)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Newsletter #17-34, February-June 1957 (Box 11, Folder 103)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Newsletter #35-50, June-October 1957 (Box 12, Folder 104)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Newsletter #51-54, November-December 1957 (Box 12, Folder 105)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Program Development, 1954-1959 (Box 12, Folder 106)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Program Study - Farm Families, 1951-1952 (Box 12, Folder 107)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Report, 1955-1957 (Box 12, Folder 108)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Rural Housing, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 109)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Special Study - Summary Sheets, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 110)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Venezuelan Agriculture and the Work of the CBR, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 111)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Club de Nutricion (Box 12, Folder 112)
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also Box 78, Folder 535.
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Newsletter #101-115, March-July 1954 (Box 12, Folder 113)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Newsletter #116-132, July 1954-January 1955 (Box 12, Folder 114)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Newsletter #133-149, January-June 1955 (Box 13, Folder 115)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Newsletter #150-166, June 1955-June 1956 (Box 13, Folder 116)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (El Hogar Que Sonamos) #1-21 (Box 13, Folder 117)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Mejor Salud por El Deporte) #1-16 (Box 13, Folder 118)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Salud, Alimentacion y Dinero para Usted) (Box 13, Folder 119)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Vitamina el Valiente - B/I) #1-14 (Box 13, Folder 120)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Vitamina el Valiente - B/I) #15-21 (Box 13, Folder 121)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Vitamina el Valiente - B/2) #1-20 (Box 13, Folder 122)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Vitamina el Valiente - B/3) #1-19 (Box 14, Folder 123)
- Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education (CIDEA) - Radio Scripts (Vitamina el Valiente - B/3) #20-31 (Box 14, Folder 124)
- International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - Annual Report, 1950-1955 (Box 14, Folder 125)
- International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - By-Laws and Incorporation Certificate (Box 14, Folder 126)
- International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - Miscellaneous, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 127)
- Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Cooperative Training Programs (Box 14, Folder 128)
- Inter-American Popular Information Program (PIIP) - Report - Role of Communication in Agricultural Economic Development by Anderson, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 129)
- Inter-American Rural Development Program (PIDR) - Planalto Presurvey, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 130)
- International Development Services, Inc. (Box 14, Folder 131)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports, 1952-1953 (Box 15, Folder 132)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports, 1954-1957 (Box 15, Folder 133)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports, 1960-1964 (Box 15, Folder 134)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Quarterly Reports, 1965-1968 (Box 15, Folder 135)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Brazil - Quarterly Reports, 1960-1961 (Box 15, Folder 136)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) - Costa Rica - Quarterly Report, January-March 1968 (Box 15, Folder 137)
- International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute - Quarterly Report, July-September 1962 (Box 15, Folder 138)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, October-December 1954 (Box 15, Folder 139)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, October-December 1955 (Box 15, Folder 140)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Report - Exhibit, October-December 1955 (Box 16, Folder 141)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, January-March 1956 (Box 16, Folder 142)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, April-June 1956 (Box 16, Folder 143)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, July-September 1956 (Box 16, Folder 144)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, October-December 1956 (Box 16, Folder 145)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, January-March 1957 (Box 16, Folder 146)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, April-June 1957 (Box 16, Folder 147)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, July-September 1957 (Box 17, Folder 148)
- Council of Rural Development (CBR) - Quarterly Reports, October-December 1957 (Box 17, Folder 149)